<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Disme: the art of tenths, or decimall arithmetike teaching how to perform all computations whatsoeuer, by whole numbers without fractions, by the foure principles of common arithmeticke: namely addition, subtraction, multiplication, and diuision. Inuented by the excellent mathematician, Simon Steuin. Published in English with wholesome additions by Robert Norton, Gent.</title>
            <title>Thiende. English</title>
            <author>Stevin, Simon, 1548-1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104599</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840332</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840332</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4828</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12970)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4828)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 861:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Disme: the art of tenths, or decimall arithmetike teaching how to perform all computations whatsoeuer, by whole numbers without fractions, by the foure principles of common arithmeticke: namely addition, subtraction, multiplication, and diuision. Inuented by the excellent mathematician, Simon Steuin. Published in English with wholesome additions by Robert Norton, Gent.</title>
                  <title>Thiende. English</title>
                  <author>Stevin, Simon, 1548-1620.</author>
                  <author>Norton, Robert, d. 1635.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By S. S[tafford] for Hugh Astley, and are to be sold at his shop at Saint Magnus corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Robert Norton, of: Stevin, Simon. Thiende.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ E³.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Arithmetic --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4828:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4828:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Robert Norton to the courteous Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I haue too often been an vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling witneſſe of the ouer-raſh diſpoſition of diuers vnaduiſed cenſurers, that would haue themſelues eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med skilfull, and yet either will not, or rather cannot doe any thing of worth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, not ſparing to cauill, detract, and iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to burthen other mens well pretended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours, with vnworthy and vndeſerued ſcoffes and ſcandalls: but in ſtead of reading to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and then to examine their true validitie, that ſo with iudgement they might cenſure them, haue crittically plaid the right Momes: And though I hope not as Iacke alone, to eſcape that<pb facs="tcp:4828:2"/>which few or none haue done before me: yet the reſpect I haue to the publike good, that you my Countrymen, ſuch as either want leiſure or lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, may become partakers of theſe excellent inuentions of that famous forraigne Authour, more preuailing with mee, then the careleſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard I haue of ſuch iniuries could hinder, I haue, as you ſee, aduentured to prouide for this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſtranger, this Engliſh welcome, and haue preferred ſome few of mine owne friends (though vnworthy) to accompany him: And ſo commending him to your courteous entertainements, doe bid you hartily farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in all courteſie, R. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="definitions">
            <pb facs="tcp:4828:2"/>
            <head>DEFINITIONS appertaining to Arithmeticall whole Numbers.</head>
            <div n="1" type="definition">
               <head>The firſt Definition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rithmeticke</hi> is the Science of Numbers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="definition">
               <head>The ſecond Definition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NVmber</hi> is that which expreſſeth the quantitie of each thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="definition">
               <head>The third Definition.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Characters</hi> by which Numbers are denoted, are ten; namely, 0 ſignifying the beginning of Number? and 1, and 2, and 3, and 4, and
5, and 6, and 7, and 8, and 9.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="definition">
               <head>The fourth Definition.</head>
               <p>EVery thrée Characters of a Number is called a
<hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> whereof the firſt are the thrée firſt towards the right hand, the ſecond, the thrée Characters next following to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the left hand: And ſo by order, for the third Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and others following, as many as there ſhall be found thrées in the Number propounded.</p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4828:3"/>
                  <head>The Explication.</head>
                  <p>AS in the number 357876297, the 297 is called the firſt Member: and 876 the ſecond: and 357 the third.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="definition">
               <head>The fift Definition.</head>
               <p>THe firſt Character of the firſt Member, beginning from the right hand to the left, doth ſimply ſignifie his owne value: the ſecond, ſo many times ten, as that contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnities: the third, ſo many times a hundred, as that containeth vnities: and the firſt Character of the ſecond Member ſo many times a thouſand, as that containeth vnities: and ſo by the tenth progreſſion of all the reſt of the Characters contained in the number propoſed.</p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>Explication.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Number propounded be 756871387130789276. Then according to this definition, the firſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter 6, maketh ſixe: and the
7 following <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and the 2 following, two hundred: and the 9, nine thouſand and ſo of the reſt. To expreſſe thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umber, place ouer euerie firſt Character of each Member (except the firſt Member) a pricke or point, as you ſée aboue: then ſay, ſeuen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fiftie ſixe thouſand thouſand thouſand thouſand thouſand, (namely, ſo many times thouſand, as there are prickes or points from 7 to the end) eight hundred ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie one thouſand thouſand thouſand thouſand, thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred eightie ſeuen thouſand thouſand thouſand, one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thirty thouſand thouſand, ſeuen hundred eightie nine thouſand, two hundred ſeuenty ſixe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="definition">
               <head>The ſixt Definition.</head>
               <p>A Whole number is either a vnitie, or a compounded multitude of vnities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="definition">
               <pb facs="tcp:4828:3"/>
               <head>The ſeuenth Definition.</head>
               <p>THe Golden Rule, or Rule of thrée, is that by which to three tearmes giuen, the fourth proportionall tearme is found.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="operations">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The operation of Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meticall whole Numbers.</head>
            <div n="1" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the Addition of whole Numbers.</hi> The firſt Probleme.</head>
               <p>ARithmeticall whole numbers being giuen to finde their
<hi>Summe, Explication propounded,</hi> let the <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> giuen to be added, be 379, and 7692, &amp; 4545, <hi>Explication required,</hi> to find their ſumme. <hi>Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> the Numbers giuen, ſhall be diſpoſed as followeth: <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo as their firſt Characters towards the right hand, ſtand directly one vnder another: and likewiſe their ſecond Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, and ſo alſo the reſt following, drawing vnder them a line: then ſhall all the Characters of the firſt ranke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the right hand be added, ſaying, 9 and 2 make 11, and 5 make 16, whereof the 6 ſhall be placed vnder the firſt ranke, and the 1 of the ſame 16, ſhall be added to the ſecond ranke, ſaying, 1 and 7 make 8, and 9 make 17, and 4 make 21. of which the 1 ſhall be placed directly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſecond ranke, and the 2 ſhall be added to the third ranke, ſaying, 2 and 3 make 5, and 6 make 11, and 5 make 16, whereof the 6 ſhall be placed vnder the third ranke, and the 1 ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<pb facs="tcp:4828:4"/>to the fourth, ſaying, 1 and 7 make 8, and 4 make 12, which ſhall be wholly placed in their ranke thus.</p>
               <p>I ſay, 12616 is the ſumme required.
<gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demonſtration:</hi> if from the thrée Numbers giuen, the two firſt be taken away, and there remaineth 4545. And if from the Summe 12616, the two firſt giuen be ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted alſo, there remaineth likewiſe 4545: But by the common <hi>Axiom,</hi> if from things equall, equall things bee ſubſtracted, their reſts ſhall be equall: And things ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted equall to things ſubſtracted, all ſhall be equall. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, 12616 is equall to thrée Numbers giuen, which is the thing required. <hi>Concluſion:</hi> Arithmeticall whole Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers being giuen to be added, we haue found their ſumme as was required.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Subſtraction of whole Numbers.</hi> The ſecond Probleme.</head>
               <p>AN Arithmeticall whole Number being giuen, out of which to ſubſtract, and another Arithmeticall whole Number to bee ſubſtracted: to finde their Reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Explication propounded,</hi> bee the Number out of which to ſubſtract, 238754207: And the number to be ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted 71572604 giuen
<hi>Explication required</hi> to finde their Reſt. <hi>Conſtruction:</hi> the Number to be ſubſtracted, ſhall be to placed vnder the Number out of which it is to bee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted,<pb facs="tcp:4828:4"/>as that the 4 ſtand directly vnder the 7, and the 0 vnder the 0, and ſo of the reſt, drawing a line betweene the numbers giuen, and another vnder the number which is to be ſubſtracted, as hereunder appeareth. <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Then beginning at the right hand, ſubſtract 4 from 7, and there reſteth 3, which ſhall be ſet directly vnder the 4, and then ſay, 0 out of 0 reſteth 0, placing 0 vnder the 0: then 6 from 2, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impoſſible, ſay, 6 from 10, and 2 (which is 12) reſteth 6, placing that vnder the 6: then 2 from 3, (true it is that you ſhould haue ſaid 2 from 4, had it not béen that you borrowed 1 from the 4 to make the other 2 to value 12) reſteth 1, placing that vnder the 2: and ſo of all the other. The diſpoſition of their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters are as héere appeareth. I ſay that 167181603 is the Reſt required. <hi>Demonſtration:</hi> adding the Reſt 167181603 to the number to be ſubſtracted 71572604, the ſumme ſhall bee equall to the number from which the ſubſtraction was made: wherfore ſéeing that 167181603 is the difference betwéene the number from which the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction was made, and the number to be ſubſtracted; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that is their Reſt which was to be demonſtrated.
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</hi> An Arithmeticall whole Number from which to be ſubſtracted, and another to ſubſtract, being giuen, wee haue found their Reſt which was required.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Multiplication of whole Numbers.</hi> The third Probleme.</head>
               <p>AN Arithmeticall whole Number giuen to be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, and another to multiply, to find their product. <hi>Explication propounded:</hi> Be the Multiplicand<pb facs="tcp:4828:5"/>or Number to be multiplied 546, and the Multiplicator or number to multiply 37. <hi>Explication required:</hi> To finde their product, Note, that for the more eaſie ſolution of this propoſition, it were neceſſary to haue in memory the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the 9 ſimple Characters among themſelues, learning them by rote out of the Table here placed, ſéeking the Multiplicand in the ſuperior line of ſquares, and the Multiplicator in the diagonall or ſlope line of ſquares: and in the common Angle anſwering them both, you ſhall find their product.
<table>
                     <head>Pythagoras Table.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                        <cell>40</cell>
                        <cell>45</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>42</cell>
                        <cell>48</cell>
                        <cell>54</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>56</cell>
                        <cell>63</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>72</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>81</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>As we would know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of 3 and 8, ſeeke 8 in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpper line, and 3 in the ſlope or dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonall: and in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Angle you ſhall find 24 their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and ſo of all the reſt, as by the Table will plainely appeare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſtruction:</hi> place the firſt numbers on the right hand (of the giuen) one directly vnder another, and then draw a line, as heere-under is done. Then ſay, 7 times 6 make 42, place 2 vnder the 7, and retaine the 4 (becauſe of the 4 tenths) in memorie: then ſay, 7 times 4 make 28, and the 4 which you had in minde, make 32, whereof place the 2 vnder the 3, and retaine 3, and ſay, 7 times 5 make 35, and 3 which was borne in minde, make 38,<pb facs="tcp:4828:5"/>which ſhall be placed in order vnder the line, as you ſée. <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap> In the like ſort ſhall the
546 bee multiplied by the 3 of the multiplicator, ſaying, 3 times 6 make 18, placing the 8 vnder the 3: and ſo of the reſt. Then ſhall bee drawne a line, adding all that is betwéene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two lines in this ſort.</p>
               <p>I ſay, that 20202 is the Product required.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demonſtration.</hi> The 20202 containeth the 37 ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times as there is vnities in the 546: therefore 20202 is the product which was to be found. <hi>Concluſion.</hi> An Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metical whole number being giuen to be multiplied, and another to multiply, we haue found their required product.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>Diuiſion of Arithmeticall whole Numbers.</hi> The fourth Probleme.</head>
               <p>AN Arithmeticall whole Number being giuen to be diuided, and another to diuide, to finde their Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Explication propounded:</hi> Be the number to bee diuided,
995, and the number to diuide, 28 giuen. <hi>Explication required:</hi> to finde their Quotient. <hi>Conſtruction:</hi> The number to be diuided (or diuident) and the number to diuide (or diuiſor) ſhall bee placed in order, drawing a crooked line, as hereunder followeth, ſaying, how many times 2 in
9? thrée times, (true it is that there are 4 times 2 in 9, and 1 remaining) but wee will ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<pb facs="tcp:4828:6"/>hereafter why we muſt ſay but three times) ſet downe 3 for the firſt Character of the Quotient, behynd the croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked line, and the 3 remayning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 9 cancelling the 2 &amp;
9: then multiply 8 by the diuiſor, by 3, the Quotient it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth 24, which ſubſtract fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 39 (here appeareth the occaſion why we ſayd that 2 is but onely 3 times in 9: for if wee had ſayd 4 times, reſting of the 9, and had multiplied 8 by 4 it would haue bene 32 which ſhould be ſubſtracted from 19 which then remayned of the diuident, which is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; therefore there muſt be ſuch a number taken, &amp; placed behind the crooked line, as that the product thereof may be ſubſtracted from the remaynder) reſteth 15, which place ouer 39, cancelling the 39, and the 8, ſo ſhall the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Characters be in this manner.
<gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Now to find the ſecond <hi>Character</hi> of the Quotient, the diuiſor muſt againe be ſet vnder the diuident, placing the
8 of the diuiſor vnder the 5 of the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and the 2 vnder the 8, ſaying how many times 2 in 15? fiue times, which 5 ſhalbe placed neere the
3 at the oblique line, for the ſecond Character of the Quotient reſteth 5 which ſhalbe placed ouer the 5 of the 15 cancelling the ſayd 15 and 2: then multiplying the diuiſor 8 by the Quotie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t 5 maketh 40, which ſubſtract from 55 remayneth 15, cancelling the 55 and the 8 and diſtinguiſhing the 15 with crooked lines from the other Characters: then draw a line neere the Quotient 35, placing ouer the ſame the ſayd remaynder, and vnder the ſame the diuiſor 28, and the diſpoſition of the Characters wilbe as appeareth aboue, I ſay that 35 15/28 is the Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient required.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demonſtration:</hi> the 35 15/28 contayneth the vnity ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as the 995 contayneth the diuiſor 28: therefore 35 15/28 is the Quotient required which was to be demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Concluſion:</hi> an Arithmeticall whole nomber for diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,<pb facs="tcp:4828:6"/>and one for diuiſor giuen, we haue found their Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient required.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <hi>The Rule of Three, or Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Rule of Arithmeticall whole Numbers.</hi> The fift Probleme.</head>
               <p>THrée Termes of Arithmeticall Numbers, being giuen to finde their proportionall Terme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Explication propounded:</hi> Be the thrée termes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen 234. <hi>Explication required:</hi> To finde their fourth proporcionall Terme: that is to ſay, in ſuch Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the third terme 4, as the ſecond terme 3, is to the firſt terme 2. <hi>Conſtruction:</hi> Multiply the ſecond terme 3, by the third terme 4, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> giueth the product 12: which diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by the firſt terme 2, giueth the Quotient 6: I ſay that 6 is the fourth proportionall terme required. <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration:</hi> there is from 6 to 4, Reaſon ſeſquialter, and the ſame Reaſon is there from 3 to 2: therefore 6 is the fourth proportionall terme to be demonſtrated.
<hi>Concluſion:</hi> thrée Arithmeticall numbers being giuen, wee haue found their fourth proportionall terme required.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:4828:7"/>
            <head>The Preface of Simon Steuin.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To Aſtronomers, Land-meaters, Meaſurers of Tapiſtry, Gaudgers, Stereometers in generall, Monty-Maſters, and to all Marchants,</salute>
               <signed>Simon Steuin</signed>
               <salute>wiſheth health.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any ſeeing the ſmalnes of this Book, and conſidering your worthynes to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is dedicated, may perchance eſteeme this our conceyte abſurd: But if the proportion be conſidered, the ſmall quantity hereof compared to humane imbecility, and the great vtility vnto high and ingenious intendiments, it will be found to haue made compariſon of the extreame tearmes, which permit not any conuerſion of proportion. But what of that? is this an admirable inuention? No cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly: for it is ſo meane, as that it ſcant deſerueth the name of an inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for as the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tryman by chance ſometime findeth a great treaſure, without any vſe of ſkill or cunning, ſo hath it hapned herein. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any will thinke, that I vaunt my ſelfe of my knowledge, becauſe of the explicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe vtilities, out of doubt, he ſheweth himſelfe to haue neyther iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vnderſtanding, nor knowledge to diſcerne<pb facs="tcp:4828:7"/>ſimple things from ingenious inuentions, but he (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) ſeemeth enuious of the common benefite: yet howſoeuer, it were not fit to omit the benefit hereof, for the inconuenience of ſuch calumny. But as the Mariner hauing by hap found a certaine vnknowne Iſland, ſpareth not to declare to his Prince the riches and profits thereof; as the fayre fruits, precious mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls, pleaſant champions, &amp;c. and that without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of Philautry: euen ſo ſhall we ſpeake freely of the great vſe of this inuention; I call it great, being greater then any of you expect to come from me. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then that the matter of this Diſme (the cauſe of the name whereof ſhalbe declared by the firſt difini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion following) is number, the vſe and effects of which, yourſelues ſhall ſufficiently witnes by your continuall experiences, therefore it were not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to vſe many words thereof: for the Aſtrologer knoweth, that the world is become by computation Aſtronomicall (ſeing it teacheth the Pilot the eleuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Equator and of the Pole, by meanes of the declination of the Sunne, to deſcribe the true Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titudes, ſituatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; diſtances of places, &amp;c.) a Paradiſe, abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in ſome places with ſuch things as the Earth cannot bring forth in other. But as the ſweet is neuer without the ſowre: ſo the trauayle in ſuch computations cannot be vnto him hidden, namely, in the buſy multiplications and diuiſions which proceed of the 60 progreſſion of degrees, minutes, ſeconds, thirds, &amp;c. And the Surueyor or Land-meater knoweth, what great benefite the world<pb facs="tcp:4828:8"/>receyueth from his ſcience, by which many diſſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and difficulties are auoyded, which otherwiſe would ariſe by reaſon of the vnknowne capacity of Land: beſides, he is not ignorant (eſpecially whoſe buſines and imployment is great) of the troubleſome multiplications of Roods, Feete, and oftentimes of ynches, the one by the other, which not onely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſteth, but alſo often (though he be very well experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced) cauſeth error, tending to the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage of both parties, as alſo to the diſcredit of Land-meater or ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyor, and ſo for the Money-maſters, Marchants and each one in his buſines: therefore how much they are more worthy, and the meanes to attayne them the more laborious, ſo much the greater and better is this Diſme, taking away thoſe difficulties: But howe? it teacheth (to ſpeake in a word) the eaſy performance of all reckonings, computations, &amp; accounts, without broken numbers, which can happen in mans buſines, in ſuch ſort, as that the foure Principles of Arithmetick namely, <hi>Addition, Subſtractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Multiplication, &amp; Deviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> by whole numbers, may ſatiſfie theſe effects, afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the like facility vnto thoſe that vſe Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters. Now if by thoſe meanes wee gaine the time which is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, if hereby that be ſaued which otherwiſe ſhould be loſt, if ſo, the paines, controuerſy, error, dammage, and other inconueniences commonly hapning ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, be eaſed, or taken away, then I leaue it willingly vnto your iudgements to be cenſured: and for that, that ſome may ſay that certaine inuentions at the firſt ſeeme good, which when they come to be practized,
<pb facs="tcp:4828:8"/>effect nothing of worth, as it often hapneth to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of ſtrong mouing, which ſeeme good in ſmall proofes and modells, when in great, or comming to the effect, they are not worth a Button: whereto we anſwere, that herein is no ſuch doubt: for expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience dayly ſheweth the ſame: namely, by the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize of diuers expert Land-meaters of
<hi>Holland,</hi> vnto whom we haue ſhewed it, who (laying aſide that which each of them had, according to his owne man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, inuented to leſſen their paines in their computati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) do vſe the ſame to their great contentment, and by ſuch fruit as the nature of it witneſſeth, the due ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect neceſſarily followeth: The like ſhall alſo happen to each of your ſelues vſing the ſame as they doe: meane while liue in all felicity.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <head>The Argument.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Diſme</hi> hath two parts, that is, <hi>Definitions</hi> &amp; <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations:</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt definition is declared what
<hi>Diſme</hi> is, by the ſecond, third, and fourth, what <hi>Comencement, Prime, Second &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Diſme</hi> numbers are: the
<hi>Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is declared by foure propoſitions, <hi>The Addition, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, Multiplication</hi> and <hi>Deuiſion</hi> of
<hi>Diſme</hi> numbers. The order whereof may be ſucceſſiuely repreſented by this Table.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="8">The Diſme hath two parts.</cell>
                     <cell rows="4">Definitions, as what is </cell>
                     <cell>Diſme,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Comencement,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Prime, Second &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Diſme nomber.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="4">Operations or Practize of the</cell>
                     <cell>Addition,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Subſtraction,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Multiplication,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Deuiſion.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4828:9"/>And to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> end the premiſes may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better be explaned, there ſhalbe hereunto an Appendix adioyned, declaring the vſe of the <hi>Diſme</hi> in many things by certaine examples, and alſo definitions and operations, to teach ſuch as doe not already know the vſe and practize of <hi>Numeration,</hi> and the foure principles of common Arithmetick, in whole numbers, namely, <hi>Addition, Subſtraction, Multiplication,</hi> &amp; <hi>Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> together with the <hi>Golden Rule,</hi> ſufficient to inſtruct the moſt ignorant in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſuall practize of this <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Diſme</hi> or Decimall Arithmeticke.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <head>The firſt Part. <hi>Of the Definitions of the Diſmes.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="definition">
               <head>The firſt Definition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DIſme</hi> is a kind of Arithmeticke, inuented by the tenth progreſſion, conſiſting in Characters of Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers; whereby a certaine number is deſcribed, and by which alſo all accounts which happen in humane affayres, are diſpatched by whole numbers, without fractions or broken numbers.</p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>Explication.</head>
                  <p>LEt the certaine number be one thouſand, one hundred and eleuen, deſcribed by the Characters of Cyphers thus 1111, in which it apeareth that ech 1 is the 10th part of his precedent character 1: likewiſe in 2378, each vnity of 8 is the tenth of each vnity of 7, and ſo of all the others: But becauſe it is conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we would ſpeake, haue names, and that this maner of<pb facs="tcp:4828:9"/>computation is found by the conſideration of ſuch tenth or diſme progreſſion; that is, that it conſiſteth therein entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as ſhall hereafter appeare: Wee call this Treatiſe fitly by the name of <hi>Diſme,</hi> whereby all accounts hapning in the affayres of man, may be wrought and effected without fractions or broken numbers, as hereafter appeareth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="definition">
               <head>The ſecond Definition.</head>
               <p>EVery number propounded, is called <hi>Comencement,</hi> woſe ſigne is thus (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>).</p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>Explication.</head>
                  <p>BY example, a certaine number is propounded of three hundred ſixty foure: we call the 364 <hi>Comencements,</hi> deſcribed thus 364 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) and ſo of all other like.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="definition">
               <head>The third Definition.</head>
               <p>ANd each tenth part of the vnity of the <hi>Comencement,</hi> wee call the <hi>Prime,</hi> whoſe ſigne is thus (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>), and each tenth part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnity of the <hi>Prime,</hi> we call the <hi>Second,</hi> whoſe ſigne is (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), and ſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other: each tenth part of the vnity of the precedent ſigne, alwayes in order, one further.</p>
               <div type="explication">
                  <head>Explication.</head>
                  <p>AS 3 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) 9 (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>) that is to ſay, 3
<hi>Primes,</hi> 7 <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds,</hi> 5 <hi>Thirds,</hi> 9 <hi>Fourths,</hi> and ſo proceeding infinitly: but to ſpeake of their valew, you may note, that according to this definition, the ſayd numbers are 3/10 7/100 5/1000
9/10000, together 3759/10000 and likewiſe 8 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 9 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) are worth 8 9/10 3/100 7/1000 together 8 937/1000 and ſo of other like. Alſo you may vnderſtand, that in this <hi>Diſme</hi> we vſe no<pb facs="tcp:4828:10"/>fractions, and that the multitude of ſignes, except (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer exceede 9: as for example, not 7 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 12 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) but in their place 8 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), for they valew as much.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="definition">
               <head>The fourth Definition.</head>
               <p>THe numbers of the ſecond and third <hi>Definitions</hi> before going, are generally called <hi>Diſme</hi> numbers.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the Definitions.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>The ſecond part of the Diſme. <hi>Of the Operation or Practize.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>The firſt propoſition of Addition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DIſme numbers being giuen how to adde them to find their ſumme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The explication propounded;</hi> there are 3 orders of
<hi>Diſme</hi> numbers giuen, of which the firſt 27 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>), 8 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>), 4 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), 7 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>), the ſecond 37 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>), 8 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>), 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), 5 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>), the third 875 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>), 7 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>)
8 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), 2 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>). <hi>The explication required,</hi> we muſt find their totall ſumme.</p>
               <div type="construction">
                  <head>Conſtruction.</head>
                  <p>The numbers giuen, muſt be placed in order as here adioyning, <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> adding them in the vulgar maner of adding of whole numbers in this maner: The ſumme (by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt Probleme of Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick following) is 941504, which are (that which the ſignes aboue the numbers do ſhew) 941 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 0 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>). I ſay, they are the ſumme required. <hi>Demonſtration:</hi> the<pb facs="tcp:4828:10"/>27 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) giuen, make by the 3 <hi>Definition</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 27 8/10 4/100 7/1000, together 27 847/1000, and by the ſame reaſon, the 37 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) ſhall make 37 875/1000, and the 875 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) will make
875 782/1000, which thrée num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers make by common addition of vulgar Arithmeticke 941 304/1000. But ſo much is the ſumme 941 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 0 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>)
4 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>): therefore it is the true ſumme to be demonſtrated.
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion:</hi> Then <hi>Diſme numbers</hi> being giuen to bee added, wee haue found their ſumme, which is the thing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                  <p>Note, that if in the number giuen, there want ſome ſignes of their naturall order, the place of the defectant ſhal be filled. As for example, let the numbers giuen bee 8 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 6 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) and 5 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>):
<gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in which, the latter wanted the ſigne of (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>), in the place thereof ſhall 0 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) bee put, take then for that latter number giuen 5 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 0 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) adding them in this ſort.</p>
                  <p>This aduertiſement ſhall alſo ſerue in the thrée follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing propoſitions, wherein the order of the defayling figures muſt be ſupplied, as was done in the former example.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>The ſecond Propoſition. Of Subſtraction.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Diſme</hi> number being giuen to ſubſtract: another leſſe <hi>Diſme</hi> number giuen out of the ſame to finde their reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4828:11"/>
                  <hi>Explication propounded:</hi> be the numbers giuen 237 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) &amp; 59 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 9 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) <hi>The Explicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> required; to find their reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſtruction:</hi> the numbers giuen ſhalbe placed in this ſort, ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting according to vulgar maner of ſubſtractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of whole nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, thus <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>The reſt is 177839 which valueth as the ſignes ouer them do denote 177 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 9 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>), I affirme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to be the reſt required.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demonſtration:</hi> the 237 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) make by the third <hi>Definition of this Diſme,</hi> 237 5/10 7/100 8/1000 to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether 237, 578/1000 and by the ſame reaſon, the 59 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 9 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) value 59 749/1000 which ſubſtracted from 237 578/1000 there reſteth
177 839/1000 but ſo much doth 177 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 9 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) value: that is then the true reſt which ſhould be made manifeſt. <hi>Concluſion: a Diſme</hi> being giuen, to ſubſtract it out of another <hi>Diſme</hi> number, and to know the reſt, which we haue found.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>The third Propoſition: of Multiplication.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Diſme</hi> number being giuen to be multiplied, and a multiplicator giuen to find their product:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Explication propounded:</hi> be the number to be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied 32 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), and the multiplicator 89 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 6 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Explication required:</hi> to find the product.
<hi>Conſtruction:</hi> the giuen numbers are to be placed as here is ſhewed, <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap> multiplying according to the vulgar maner of multiplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by whole nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, in this maner,<pb facs="tcp:4828:11"/>giuing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> product, 29137122: <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Now to know how much they value, ioyne the two laſt ſignes together as the one (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) and the other (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) alſo, which together make (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>), and ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the laſt ſigne of the product ſhall be (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>) which being knowne, all the reſt are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo knowne by their continued order. So that the product required, is 2913 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 1 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>).</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demonſtration:</hi> The number giuen to be multiplyed, 32 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) (as appeareth by the third <hi>Definition</hi> of this
<hi>Diſme</hi>) 32 5/10 7/100 together 32 57/100: and by the ſame reaſon the multiplicator 89 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 6 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) value 89 46/100 by the ſame, the ſaid 32 57/100 multiplied, giueth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct 2913, 7122/10000 But it valueth 2913 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 1 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>). It is then the true product which we were to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate. But to ſhew why (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) multiplied by (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) giueth the product (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>) which is the ſumme of their numbers, alſo why (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>) by (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>) produceth (<hi rend="sup">9</hi>), and why (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) by (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) produceth (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) &amp;c. Let vs take
2/10 and 3/100 which (by the third <hi>Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of this
<hi>Diſme</hi>) are 2 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) their product is 6/10000 which value by the ſaid third <hi>Definition</hi> 6 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>), multiplying then (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) by (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) the product is (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) namely a ſigne compounded of the ſumme of the numbers of the ſignes giuen.</p>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>Concluſion.</head>
                  <p>A <hi>Diſme</hi> number to multiply, and to be multiplyed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen, we haue found the product, as we ought.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="note">
                  <head>Note.</head>
                  <p>IF the latter ſigne of the number to bee multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, bee vnequall to the latter ſigne of the multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, as for example, the one 3 (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">6</hi>), the<pb facs="tcp:4828:12"/>other 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), they ſhal he handled as aforeſayd, and the diſpoſition thereof ſhalbe thus.
<gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <head>The fourth Propoſition: of Diuiſion.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Diſme number</hi> for the diuident, and diuiſor, being giuen to find the Quotient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Explication propoſed:</hi> let the number for the diuident be 3 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>) and the diuiſor 9 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 6 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>).
<hi>Explication required:</hi> to find their Quotient.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>COnſtruction:</hi> the numbers giuen diuided (omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſignes) according to the vulgar maner of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding of whole numbers, giueth the Quotient, 3587; now to know what they value; the latter ſigne of the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) muſt be ſubſtracted from the latter ſigne of the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent which is (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>), reſteth (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) for the latter ſigne of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Character of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quotient, which being ſo knowne, all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt are alſo manifeſt by their continued order, thus 3 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) are the Quotient required.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEmonſtration:</hi> the number diuident giuen 3 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>) maketh (by the third <hi>Definition</hi> of this <hi>Diſme</hi>) 3 4/10 4/100 3/1000 5/10000 2/100000 together 3
44352/100000 and by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame reaſon, the diuiſor 9 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 6 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) valueth
96/100, by which 3 44352/100000 being diuided, giueth the Quotient 3 587/1000; but the ſayd Quotient valueth 3 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>): there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is the true Quotient to be demonſtrated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concluſion:</hi> a Diſme number being giuen for the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent<pb facs="tcp:4828:12"/>and diuiſor, we haue found the Quotient required.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> if the diuiſors ſignes be higher then the ſignes of the diuident, there may be as many ſuch Cyphers 0 ioyned to the diuident as you will, or many as ſhalbe neceſſary: as for example,
<gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) are to be diuided by 4 (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>), I place after the 7 certaine 0 thus 7000, diuiding them as aforeſayd, &amp; in this ſort it giueth for the Quotient 1750 (<hi rend="sup">7</hi>).</p>
               <p>It hapneth alſo ſometimes, that the Quotient cannot be expreſſed by whole numbers, as 4 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) diuided by 3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) in this ſort,
<gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap> whereby appeareth, that there will infinitly come from the 3 the reſt of ⅓ and in ſuch an accident you may come ſo neere as the thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, omitting the remaynder, it is true, that 13 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>)
3 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 3⅓ (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) &amp;c. ſhalbe the perfect Quotient required: but our intention in this <hi>Diſme</hi> is to worke all by whole num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: for ſeing that in any affayres, men reckon not of the thouſandth part of a mile, grayne, &amp;c. as the like is alſo vſed of the principall Geometricians, and Aſtronomers, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putacions of great conſequence, as
<hi>Ptolome</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohannes Monta-regio</hi> haue not deſcribed their Tables of Arches, Chords, or Sines, in extreme perfection (as poſſibly they might haue done by <hi>Multinomall</hi> numbers,) becauſe that imperfection (conſidering the ſcope and end of thoſe Tables) is more conuenient then ſuch perfection.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note</hi> 2. the extraction of all kinds of Roots may alſo be made by theſe <hi>Diſme</hi> numbers: as for example, To ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the ſquare roote of 5 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) 9 (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>), which is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the vulgar maner of extraction in this ſort, <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and the root ſhalbe 2 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), for the moitye or<pb facs="tcp:4828:13"/>halfe of the latter ſigne of the numbers giuen, is alwayes the latter ſigne of the roote: wherefore if the latter ſigne giuen were of a number imper: the ſigne of the next follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing ſhalbe added, and then it ſhalbe a number per; and then extract the Root as afore. Likewiſe in the extraction of the Cubique Roote, the third part of the latter ſigne giuen ſhalbe alwayes the ſigne of the Roote: and ſo of all other kind of Roots.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>The end of the Diſme.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>The Appendix.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <p>SEing that we haue already deſcribed the Diſme, we will now come to the vſe thereof, ſhewing by vi. Articles, how all computations which can hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in any mans buſines, may be eaſily performed thereby: beginning firſt to ſhew how they are to be put in practize, in the caſting vp of the content or quantity of Land meaſured as followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>The firſt Article, of the Computations of Land-meating.</head>
               <p>CAll the Pearch or Rood alſo <hi>Comencement,</hi> which is 1 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>), diuiding that into 10 equall parts, whereof each one ſhalbe 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>); the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuide each prime againe<pb facs="tcp:4828:13"/>into 10 equall parts, each of which ſhalbe 1 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>); and againe each of them into 10 equall parts, and each of them ſhalbe 1 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>); proceeding further ſo, if neede be; but in Land-mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, diuiſions of ſeconde wilbe ſmall enough: yet for ſuch things as require more exactnes, as Fathome of the Lead, Bodyes &amp;c. there may be thirds vſed: and for as much as the greater number of Land-meaters vſe not the Pole, but a chayne line of three, foure or fiue Perch long mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon the yard of their croſſe ſtaffe certaine feete 5 or 6 with fingers, palmes &amp;c. the like may be done here: for in the place of their fiue or ſixe feete with their fingers, they may put 5 or 6 <hi>primes</hi> with their
<hi>ſeconds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THis being ſo prepared, theſe ſhalbe vſed in meaſuring, without regarding the feete and fingers of the Pole, according to the Cuſtome of the place: &amp; that which muſt be added, ſubſtracted, multiplied or diuided according to this meaſure, ſhalbe performed according to the doctrine of the precedent examples.</p>
               <p>AS for example, we are to adde 4. tryangles or ſurfaces of Land, whereof the firſt 345 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond 872 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>)
3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), the third 615 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth 956 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 6 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>);
<gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>THeſe being added according to the manner declared in the firſt <hi>Propoſition</hi> of this <hi>Diſme</hi> in this ſort, their ſumme wil be 2790 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) or Perches 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 9 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), the ſayd Roods or Perches, diuided according to the cuſtome of the place; (for euery Acre contayneth certaine Perches) by the number of perches you ſhall haue the Acres ſought. BVt if one would know how many feete and fingers are in the 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 9 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) (that which Land-meater ſhall need to doe but once, and that at the end of the caſting vp of the proprietaries, although moſt men eſteeme it vnneceſſary to make any mention of feete and fingers) it will appeare
<pb facs="tcp:4828:14"/>vpon the Pole how many feete and fingers (which are marked, ioyning the tenth part vpon another ſide of the Rood) accord with themſelues.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond, out of 57 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) ſubſtracted 32 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) it may be effected according to the ſecond propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this <hi>Diſme,</hi> in this maner: <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>In the third (for multiplication of the ſides of certaine Triangles and Quadrangles) multiply 8 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), by 7 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 2 this may be performed according to the third propoſition of this
<hi>Diſme,</hi> in this manner: <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>And giueth for the product or ſuperfices 65 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) &amp;c.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Deuide 367 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 6 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) by 26 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) according to the fourth propoſition of this <hi>Diſme:</hi> ſo the Quotient giueth from
<hi>A,</hi> towards <hi>B,</hi> 13 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 9 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), which is <hi>A E.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if wee will, wee may come neerer (although it bée needles) by the ſecond note of the fourth Propoſition,<pb facs="tcp:4828:14"/>the demonſtrations of all theſe examples are alreadie made in their propoſitions. <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>The II. Article: of the Computations of the meaſures of Tapiſtry, or Cloth.</head>
               <p>THe Ell of the Meaſurer of Tapiſtrie or cloth, ſhall be to him 1 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>), the which he ſhall deuide (vpon the ſide whereon the partitions, which are according to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Towne, is not ſet out) as is done aboue on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pole of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Land meater, namely into 10 equall parts, whereof each ſhall be 1 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>), then each 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) into 10 equall partes, of which each ſhall be 1 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) &amp;c. And for the practiſe ſeeing that theſe examples doe altogether accord with thoſe of the firſt Article of Landmeating, it is thereby ſufficiently manifeſt, ſo as we need not here make any mention againe of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>The III. Article: of the Computations, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to Gaudging, and the meaſures of all Liquor veſſels.</head>
               <p>ONe <hi>Ame</hi> (which maketh 100 pots <hi>Antwerp</hi>) ſhalbe 1 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>), the ſame ſhall be deuided in length and deepnes, into 10 equall parts (namely, equall to reſpect of the wine, not of the Rod; of which the parts of the pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ditie ſhalbe vnequall) &amp; each part ſhalbe 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) containing 10 pots, then again each 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) into 10, parts equal as afore, and each will make 1 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) worth 1 pot, then each 1 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) into 10. equal parts making each 1 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>).</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4828:15"/>Now the Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being ſo deuided, to know the content of the Tunne, multiply and worke as in the precedent firſt Article, of which (being ſufficiently manifeſt) we will not ſpeake here any farther.</p>
               <figure/>
               <p>It remaineth yet to deuide each length as <hi>B O</hi> &amp;
<hi>O C,</hi> &amp;c. into fiue, thus: Seeke the meane proportionall betweene
<hi>B M:</hi> &amp; his 10 part which ſhalbe <hi>B R:</hi> cutting <hi>B S:</hi> equal to <hi>B R:</hi> Then the length <hi>S R.</hi> noted from
<hi>B</hi> towards <hi>A:</hi> as <hi>B T:</hi> and likewiſe the length <hi>T R:</hi> from <hi>B</hi> to <hi>V:</hi> &amp; ſo of the others: &amp; in like ſort proceeding to deuide <hi>B S:</hi> and <hi>S T:</hi> &amp;c. into (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>), I ſay that <hi>B S: S T:</hi> and <hi>T V:</hi> &amp;c.<pb facs="tcp:4828:15"/>are the deſired (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) which is thus to bee demonſtrated.</p>
               <p>For that <hi>B N:</hi> is the meane proportionall line (by the
<hi>Hipotheſis</hi> betwéene <hi>B M:</hi> and his moytie, the ſquare of <hi>B N:</hi> (by the 17. propoſition of the ſixt booke of
<hi>Euclide</hi>) ſhalbe equall to the Rectangle of <hi>B M:</hi> &amp; his moytie: But the ſame Rectangle is the moytie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſquare of <hi>B M:</hi> the ſquare then of <hi>B N:</hi> is equall to the moytie of the ſquare of
<hi>B M:</hi> But <hi>B O</hi> is (by <hi>Hipotheſis</hi>) equall to <hi>B N:</hi> and <hi>B C:</hi> to <hi>B M:</hi> the ſquare then of <hi>B O:</hi> is equall to the moitie of the ſquare of <hi>B C.</hi> And in like ſort it is to be demonſtrated, that the ſquare of <hi>B S</hi> is equall to the tenth part of the ſquare of <hi>B M.</hi> Wherefore &amp;c. we haue made the demonſtration briefe, becauſe wee write not this to learners, but vnto maſters in their ſcience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>The IIII. Article: of Computations of Stereometrie in generall.</head>
               <p>TRue it is, that <hi>Gaudgerie</hi> which we haue before decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is <hi>Stereometrie</hi> (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, the Art of meaſuring of bodies) but conſidering the diuers diuiſions of the Rod, Yard, or Meaſure of the one and other, and that and this doe ſo much differ, as the
<hi>Genus</hi> and the <hi>Species:</hi> they ought by good reaſon to be diſtinguiſhed. For all <hi>Stereo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie</hi> is not <hi>Gaudgerie.</hi> To come to the point, the <hi>Stereo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrian</hi> ſhall vſe the meaſure of the towne or place, as the Yard, Ell &amp;c. with his tenne partitions, as is deſcribed in the firſt and ſecond Articles, the vſe and practiſe thereof, (as is before ſhewed) is thus: Put caſe wee haue a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drangular, Rectangular Columne to bee meaſured, the length whereof is 3 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 2 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), the breadth 2 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), the height 2 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), The queſtion is, how much the ſubſtance or matter of that Piller is: Multiply (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the doctrine of the 4. propoſition of this <hi>Diſme</hi>) the length by the bredth, &amp; the product again by the height in<pb facs="tcp:4828:16"/>this manner,
<gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>And the product appeareth to be 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>) 8 (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>).</p>
               <p>NOte, ſome ignorant (and vnderſtanding not that wee ſpeake here) of the Principles of <hi>Stereometry,</hi> may maruayle wherefore it is ſayd, that the greatnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid colu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n is but 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) &amp;c. ſeing that it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayneth more then 180 cubes, of which the length of each ſide is 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>), he muſt know that the body of one yard is not a body of 10 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) as a yard in length, but 1000 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) in reſpect whereof 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth 100 Cubes, each of 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) as the like is ſufficiently manifeſt amongſt Land-meats in ſurfaces: for when they ſay 2 Roodes, 3 Feete of Land, it is not barelymeant 2 ſquare Roods, and three ſquare feete, but two Roods (and counting but 12 feete to the Rood) 36 feete ſquare: therefore if the ſayd Queſtion had beene how many Cubes each being 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) was in the greatnes of the ſayd Piller, the ſolution ſhould haue bene fitted accordingly, conſidering that each of theſe 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) doth make 100 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) of thoſe; and each 1 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) of theſe maketh 10 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) of thoſe &amp;c. or otherwiſe, if the tenth part of the yard be the greateſt meaſure that the
<hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reometrian</hi> propoſeth, he may call it 1 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>), and ſo as aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:4828:16"/>
               <head>The fift Article; of Aſtronomicall Computations.</head>
               <p>THe ancient Aſtronomers hauing diuided their Circles each into
360 degrees, they ſaw, that the Aſtronomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Computations of them with their parts was too labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: and therefore they diuided alſo each degree into cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine parts, and thoſe againe into as many, &amp;c. to the end thereby to worke alwayes by whole numbers, chuſing the 60th progreſſion, becauſe that 60 is a number meaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by many whole meaſures, namely,
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 10, 12, 15, 20, 30: but if experience may be credited (we ſay with reuerence to the venerable antiquity, and moued with the common vtility) the 60th progreſſion was not the moſt conuenient, (at leaſt) amongſt thoſe that in nature conſiſt potentially, but the tenth which is thus: we call the 360 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees alſo <hi>Comencements,</hi> expreſſing them ſo 360 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>), and each of them a degree 12 1 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) to be diuided into 10 equall parts, of which each ſhall make 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>), and againe each 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) into 10 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) and ſo of the reſt, as the like hath already bene often done.</p>
               <p>Now this diuiſion being vnderſtood, we may deſcribe more eaſily that we promiſed in <hi>Addition, Subſtraction, Multiplication,</hi> and <hi>Diuiſion;</hi> but becauſe there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene the operation of theſe, and the foure for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer propoſitions of this booke, it would but be loſſe of time, and therefore they ſhall ſerue for examples of this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: yet adding thus much, that we will vſe this maner of partition in all the Tables &amp; computations which happen in Aſtronomy, ſuch as we kepe to diuulge in our vulgar Germane Language, which to the moſt rich adorned and perfect Tongue of all other, &amp; of the moſt ſingularity, of which we attend a more abundant demonſtration, then <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> haue made thereof in the
<hi>Bewysconſt</hi> and <hi>Dialectique,</hi> lately diuulged, and haue in the leaſe follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing placed a neceſſary Table, for the reducing of the
<pb facs="tcp:4828:17"/>minutes, ſeconds, &amp;c. of the 60, progreſſion, into primes, ſeconds, &amp;c. of the tenth progreſſion: the vſe whereof follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth.</p>
               <div type="application">
                  <head>The vſe of this Table.</head>
                  <p>VVHen any number of minutes, ſeconds, thirds, fourths &amp;c. of the 60th progreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are giuen to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into the primes, ſeconds, thirds, &amp;c. of the tenth progreſſion, ſeeke the giuen number in this Table, or if the number be not there to be found, take the neereſt: if none be there great enough, take halfe or one quarter of the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: if there be none ſmall enough, double, treble, or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>druple, the giuen, and then as aforeſayd ſeeke the neereſt number thereunto in the Table, and the two numbers in whoſe common Angle the giuen number is found, or nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt found, ſhall ſhew you the quantity and quality of the ſubdiuiſions of the ten progreſſions proper to that giuen number, namely, the number ſtanding in the toppe or front of the table directly ouer it, ſhall ſhew the quantity, and the number directly againſt it in the firſt Columne toward the left hand, ſhall denote the quality; as for example, be the pronumber giuen <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſeeke it in the Table, and you ſhall find to ſtand in the front directly ouer it the figure
7, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt Columne directly againſt it toward the left hand (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>): therefore according to the rule aboue mentioned, I conclude, that
<gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the 60 pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion valueth iuſt 7 (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>) of the tenth progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion &amp;c. This example I thinke ſufficient to enlighten the ingenious practizer: onely this, that if there be no number to be found in the Table, iuſt or neere the number giuen, you may take two, three or more of thoſe that will come neereſt, and ſo worke as before: as for example alſo, be the number giuen <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the 60 progreſſion; you ſhall find them all by taking 4 of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vnder 3, to be <gap reason="math" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the tenth progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: and ſo with a ſmall diligence may any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther number of the one progreſſion be reduced into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which I omit to ſpeake any further of at this time.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:4828:17"/>
               <head>The ſixt Article; of the Computations of Money-maſters, Marchants, and of all eſtates in generall.</head>
               <p>TO the end we ſpeake in generall and briefly of the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me and contents of this Article, it muſt be alwayes vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all meaſures (be they of length, liquors, of mony &amp;c.) be parted by the tenth progreſſion, and each notable ſpecies of them, ſhalbe called
<hi>Comencement:</hi> as a <hi>Marke,</hi> comence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of weight, by the which
<hi>Siluer</hi> and <hi>Gold</hi> are wayed, <hi>Pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> of other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weights, <hi>Liuers-degros</hi> in <hi>Flanders, Pound</hi> ſterling in
<hi>England, Ducat</hi> in <hi>Spaine &amp;c. Comence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of Money: the higheſt ſigne of the <hi>Marke</hi> ſhalbe (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>), for 1 (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>) ſhall weigh about the halfe of one <hi>Es</hi> of <hi>Antwerp,</hi> the (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) ſhall ſerue for the higheſt ſigne of the <hi>Liure de gros,</hi> ſeing that 1 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) maketh leſſe then the quarter of one <hi>DS.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſubdiuiſions of weight to weigh al things, ſhalbe (in place of the halfe pound, quarter, halfe quarter, ounce, halfe ounce, eſterlin, graine, <hi>Es,</hi> &amp;c. of each ſigne, 5, 3, 2, 1, that is to ſay, that after the pound or 1 (<hi rend="sup">0</hi>) ſhall follow the halfe pound or 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>), then the 3 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) then the 2 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) then the 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>), and the like ſubdiuiſions haue alſo the 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) and the other following.</p>
               <p>VVE thinke it neceſſary, that each ſubdiuiſion, what matter ſoeuer the ſubiect be of, be called <hi>Prime, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, Third,</hi> &amp;c. and that becauſe it is notable vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> being multiplied by the <hi>Third,</hi> giueth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct the
<hi>Fifth</hi> (becauſe two and three make fiue, as is ſayd before) alſo the <hi>Third</hi> diuided by the <hi>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> giueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<hi>Prime &amp;c.</hi> that which ſo properly cannot be done by any other names: but when it ſhalbe named for diſtinction of the matters (as to ſay, halfe an Ell, half a pound, halfe a pynte &amp;c.) we may call them
<hi>Prime of Marc, Second of Marc, Second of Pound, Second</hi> of Ell, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But to the'nd wee may giue example, ſuppoſe 1 <hi>Mark</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4828:18"/>of <hi>Gold</hi> value 36 lib. 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) the Queſtion what valueth 8 <hi>Marks</hi> 3 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>): multiply 3653 by 8354 giuing the product by the fourth <hi>Propoſition</hi> (which is alſo the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution required) 395 lib. 1 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 7 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) 1 (<hi rend="sup">3</hi>); as for the 6 (<hi rend="sup">4</hi>) and 2 (<hi rend="sup">5</hi>) they are here of no eſtimation.</p>
               <p>SVppoſe againe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 2 Ells and 3 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) coſt 3 lib. 2 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 5 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> queſtion is, what ſhall 7 Ells 5 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 3 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) coſt: multiply according to the cuſtome the laſt terme giuen by the ſecond, and diuide the product by the firſt, that is to ſay, 753 by 325 maketh 244725, which diuided by 23, giueth the Quotient and Solution 10 lib. 6 (<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) 4 (<hi rend="sup">2</hi>).</p>
               <p>VVE could alſo more amply demonſtrate by eaſie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of broken numbers, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> compariſon and great difference of the facility of this more then that, but we will paſſe them ouer for breuity ſake.</p>
               <p>LAſtly, it may be ſayd, that there is ſome difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene this laſt ſixt Article, and the 5 precedent Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which is, that each one may exerciſe for them ſelues the tenth partition of the ſaid precedent 5 Articles, thoughſt be not giuen by the Magiſtrate of the place as a generall order, but it is not ſo in this latter: for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples hereof, are vulgar computations, which do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt continually happen to euery man, to whom it were neceſſary that the ſolution ſo found, were of each accepted for good and lawfull: Therefore conſidering the ſo great vſe, it would be a commendable thing, if ſome of thoſe who expect the greateſt commodity, would ſolicit to put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in execution to effect, namely, that ioyning the vulgar par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions that are now in weight, meaſures, and moneyes (continuing ſtill each Capitall meaſure, waight and Coyne in all places vnaltred) that the ſame tenth progreſſion might be lawfully ordained by the ſuperiors, for euery one that would vſe the ſame it might alſo do well, if the values of Moneys, principally the new Coynes, might be valued and reckned vpon certayne <hi>Primes, Seconds, Thirds &amp;c</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4828:18"/>But if all this be not put in practize ſo ſoone as we could wiſh, yet it will firſt content vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it wil be beneficiall to our ſucceſſors, if future men ſhal hereafter be of ſuch nature as our predeceſſors, who were neuer negligent of ſo great aduantage. Secondly, that it is not vnneceſſary for each in particular, for ſo much as concerneth him, for that they may all deliuer them ſelues when they will, from ſo much and ſo great labour. And laſtly, although the effects of the ſixt Article appeare not immediatly, yet it may be; and in the meane time may each one exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe himſelfe in the fiue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, ſuch as ſhalbe moſt conuenient for them; as ſome of them haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the Appendix.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
